-Hey! -We get it, already!
-喂！ -我们知道错了！
-Let go! -We give up!
-快走！ -我们认栽！
Sorry for picking on his dog!
对不起 不该欺负他的狗
We won't do it again!
我们再也不敢了！
Damn it! What the hell? He's just a kid!
可恶 搞什么啊？ 一个小鬼居然这么厉害
Let's get going, already!
快走吧！
Thank you, Akira!
谢谢你 阿辉
The evils of the world can't stand up to me!
世间所有邪恶都得在我面前跪地求饶
The superhero of justice!
吾乃超级英雄 正义的化身
Just leave it to Akiraiger!
一切都包在我辉狮虎侠身上！
35. REMEMBER MY CHILDHOOD DREAM
（35 回忆起儿时的梦想）
Hey, Akira, this is really bad. All of Japan's like this, for real!
喂 阿辉 这下完了 全日本都沦陷了
I don't think there are any urban areas, or rather,
我看现在没有一个城市是安全的
anywhere in the country that's safe anymore.
甚至可以说 全国都没有安全的地方了
It seems the Self-Defense Force managed to isolate them in Hokkaido!
自卫队似乎 在北海道隔离出了安全区！
And a number of villages in the mountains were able to seal off access tunnels!
山里也有一部分村庄 封锁了进出的隧道
That means my family might still be safe.
也就是说 我的家人也许仍平安无事
They're in Gunma, "Kanto's best kept secret!"
毕竟他们住在号称 “关东神秘瑰宝”的群马
So, why did you decide to go blond?
你为什么要把头发染成金色？
Seeing how you're doing what you've always wanted,
看到你一件件完成自己想做的事
I figured I needed to do the same.
我也想像你一样
Kind of like my way of saying I'm exiting the grind.
这算是我的宣言吧 我要跳出常规
Besides, if I'm gonna become a comic, this should make an impact, right?
再说了 既然要当谐星 这种发色更让人眼前一亮 对吧？
Hey, Kencho…
喂 阿宪
I'm…
我…
thinking of becoming a superhero.
我想当超级英雄
-I said, I want to become a-- -I heard you the first time.
-我说 我想当… -我听见你刚才说的了
By "superhero," do you mean like Spider-Man?
“超级英雄”是指 像蜘蛛侠那样的吗？
That's right!
没错！
This morning, I remembered something from my childhood.
今天早上 我想起了小时候的一件事
And that was…
从那时起…
Go! That's it!
上啊！就是这样！
…to fight danger and save those in need in a kickass costume, for no reward.
就对于穿着一身帅气的战服 不计回报地锄强扶弱、除暴安良
That was the kind of hero I dreamed of becoming!
我开始梦想成为那样的英雄
Good idea, right? You only live once, right?
这主意很棒吧？人就该把握当下呀
A hero of justice who saves people from zombies!
当个打僵尸、救人民的正义英雄！
Would it be all right if I do it?
我可以的吧？
Sure, if you want. But you can't fly or shoot webs.
当然 如果你想的话 可是你既不会飞 也不能喷射蛛丝啊
Good point!
有道理！
I've been doing research on ways to fight zombies!
所以我一直在研究对付僵尸的方法
That's how I discovered this!
然后我发现了这个！
Now I get it.
这下我懂了
So, that's it.
原来如此
Come on, let's go, Kencho!
那就快行动起来吧 阿宪
Let's begin preparations!
开始准备作战！
What? Right now?
什么？现在吗？
Hey, at least let me get something to eat!
喂 至少先让我吃点东西吧！
36. BECOME A SUPERHERO
（36 当超级英雄）
BRED IN CAPTIVITY FOR THE FIRST TIME!
（首次人工圈养培育！）
I haven't been to one of these since I was a kid.
自从长大以后我就没来过这种地方了
Yeah!
是呀
The aquarium, huh?
水族馆是吧？
It's in pretty bad shape, isn't it?
还真是一片狼藉啊
I'd be pissing myself right now if this was still day one of the outbreak.
如果这是僵尸大爆发的第一天 我现在估计都吓得尿裤子了吧
Doesn't it feel strangely exciting walking in the back rooms of the aquarium?
走在水族馆的后室里 有种诡异的刺激感觉 不是吗？
I know what you mean!
我懂你的意思
That feeling you're doing something you shouldn't is kind of thrilling.
干一些不该干的事 就会感觉很刺激
Is it here?
在这里吗？
-This is… -Yeah!
-这是… -对！
As long as I have this, then starting today,
只要有了这个 从今天开始
I'm a superhero!
我就是超级英雄了！
It's no good! We can't go any further!
不好！前面过不去了
For now, let's wait until the zombies around us go away!
我们暂时先等周围的僵尸散开吧
No way!
不要啊！
I don't want to die.
我不想死
Are you all…
你还好…
No!
不要啊！
Someone, help…
谁来救救…
I don't want to die. I don't want to die.
我不想死
I don't want to die!
我不想死呀！
GREAT WHITE BRED IN CAPTIVITY
（圈养培育的大白鲨）
If I can make it over there, I'll be safe!
只要能跑到那边 我就安全了
I'll definitely be safe!
一定会没事的！
No. I don't want to die.
不 我不想死
I don't want to die just yet.
我还不想死呀
Are you all right, miss?
你没事吧 小姐姐？
Get going while you still can.
趁现在快逃吧
It's the end of the line, zombies!
僵尸们 休想再往前靠近一步！
Akiraiger is here!
辉狮虎侠在此！
How was that, Kencho?
我刚才帅吗 阿宪？
Well… I guess you could say you kind of have the look down.
这个…勉强算是有超级英雄的范儿吧
-So, this is what you were talking about? -Yeah!
-这就是你说的战袍？ -没错
Shark suits are diving suits designed to protect your body from shark bites.
防鲨服是为了防止被鲨鱼咬伤 而专门设计的潜水服
They're used when cleaning shark or crocodile tanks!
是给人在清理鲨鱼池和鳄鱼池时穿的
It's made from a mesh of titanium and high-strength steel fibers
它由钛金和高强度的钢纤维 混合编织而成
that act like chain mail.
就像一套现代版的锁子甲
Even large sharks can't bite through it.
就连大鲨鱼都没办法咬破
I see.
原来如此
In other words, as long as I have this suit,
也就是说 只要穿上这身战袍
I'm invulnerable to zombie bites!
我就能百分百防御僵尸的啃咬
I've become an invincible superhero!
变身成无敌超人！
Invincible, huh?
无敌吗？
More people in need of help!
还有更多人需要帮助
This way!
这边走！
It's safe inside the aquarium.
水族馆里面是安全的
It's her.
是她
Miss Risk Analyst!
强调规避风险的小姐姐！
I didn't think I would run into her here. It's a miracle.
没想到会在这里遇见她 真是奇迹呀
This must be fate.
这一定是命运的安排
Is he cosplaying?
他在玩角色扮演吗？
Akira!
阿辉！
This is the best chance to show off!
我要趁这个机会好好表现
I'm going to show her how cool--
让她看看我有多酷…
That hurts!
好痛！
-Okay, right this way. -Why does it hurt so much?
-好的 这边走 -怎么会这么痛呀？
Ouch! No!
好痛！别咬了！
I get it.
我知道了
It's puncture proof. It blocks teeth, but you'll still feel the bite.
那身衣服虽然不会被咬穿 但它能挡住牙齿 却挡不住疼痛
It hurts! Save me, Kencho!
痛死我了！阿宪 救我！
Not happening. There's only one suit, after all!
帮不了你 谁叫这里只有一套防鲨服呢？
Don't worry about us.
不必担心我们哟
Sorry, but you'll have to handle that on your own! Bye!
抱歉啦 你自己想办法解决吧 回见！
No way!
别呀！
Kencho!
阿宪！
Ouch! Stop struggling!
痛啊！别再挣扎啦！
It's over.
搞定
We should be all right for a while.
暂时应该没事了
That look…
她那眼神…
She was definitely turned off by that.
她肯定对我毫无兴趣了吧
Being a superhero is hard work.
当超级英雄可真是不容易啊
I'm safe! I thought it was all over!
总算安全了！我还以为死定了呢
We're safe for now,
目前暂时是安全了
Kencho.
阿宪
Hey, well done, hero.
嘿 干得漂亮哦 英雄
You're horrible.
你这臭小子
Don't be like that.
别这么垂头丧气嘛
You ended up being a decent hero!
你这英雄当得还不赖哟！
Something going on with her?
你认识她吗？
Well, I met her once before.
之前遇到过一次
Go talk to her.
去找她说话吧
What?
什么？
What a coincidence, running into you again.
好巧呀 又遇到你了
We met at the convenience store before!
我们之前在便利店见过
Oh, yeah. Back then…
对哦 那时候…
Yeah.
是呀
My name is Akira Tendo.
我叫天道辉
I feel like this must be fate.
我们再次相遇 一定是命运的安排
-Maybe we should exchange contact-- -Akira, was it?
-也许我们该交换联系方式… -阿辉 是吗？
Not that it's my business or anything,
或许是我多管闲事
but in what way do you benefit from saving people?
但救人对你有什么好处？
Bene…
好处…
That getup… Yes…
还有你那身装扮…是了
Psychologists call it identification.
这就是心理学所说的“自我认同”
An inferiority complex or low self-esteem
自卑或者缺乏自信
often causes people to adopt the look and mannerisms of their heroes.
往往会导致一个人 去模仿自己心目中的英雄形象
It's a psychological defense mechanism.
这是一种心理防御机制
In short…
简而言之
It's what makes men
就是那些
who are typically unvalued by society and lack self-worth
不被社会看重 缺乏自我价值感的男人
wish they could become heroes.
渴望能成为英雄的现象
Harsh.
扎心了
Hold on, how could you say such a thing?
等一下 你怎么能那么说呢？
Akira saved everyone here from those zombies.
阿辉可是刚刚从僵尸手里救了大家呀
He managed to save complete strangers from zombies this time.
这次他确实从僵尸手里 救了一群陌生人
I don't intend to deny the fact that he saved people.
我没想否认他救人的事实
But… Did you consider the danger to those truly important to you
但是 当你冲出去拯救陌生人 为自己的低自信挽尊时
when you leaped into action to mollify your low self-esteem?
有想过会将你真正在乎的人 置于怎样的危险中吗？
Additionally, "hero" isn't a title you can claim for yourself.
再说“英雄”这个头衔可不是自封的
What one person considers justice…
一个人自以为的正义…
What…
什么？
She's super argumentative and difficult to please!
她还真是能言善辩 而且超级难伺候呀！
-What? The outfit's got nothing to do-- -But, she's right.
-什么？这身服装不是你说的… -但她说得没错
-Being a hero will put Kencho in danger. -We're just trying our best here!
-我想当英雄却将阿宪置于险境 -我们只是想尽力帮助大家！
What exactly is a hero?
英雄究竟是什么？
What is a hero?
怎样才叫英雄？
Anyway…
总之
If you still can't analyze risk, you'll only lower my survivability.
如果仍然不懂得规避风险 你就只会拉低我存活的几率
I'm afraid I must decline your request to exchange contact info yet again.
恐怕这次我还是 得拒绝你交换联系方式的请求
What's that noise?
什么声音？
I'll go check it out!
我去看看
-Kencho! -What? Me too?
-阿宪！ -什么？我也要去吗？
I guess I have no choice!
真拿你没辄
What I should be doing now is…
我现在应该做的就是…
What is this? The water's…
怎么回事？这些水…
Hey, Akira!
喂 阿辉！
Over there…
那边…
A… shark?
这是…鲨鱼吗？
Wait, but it has legs.
慢着 可是它长了腿
I see.
看见了
In that case…
这样的话
What is it?
它到底是什么？
What's that?
怎么回事？
What's that noise?
那是什么声音？
Everyone, run away!
大家快跑！
It's a shark!
鲨鱼来了！
No!
不要啊！
What should I do? What would a hero do at a time like this?
我该怎么办？ 英雄在这种时候会怎么做？
At a time like this…
在这种时候…
What?
什么？
For now, we just need to make a tactical retreat, right?
目前还是得先战术性撤退 对吧？
What the hell is that?
那是个什么鬼？
It's a great white shark. Lamniformes Lamnidae!
是一条大白鲨 隶属鼠鲨目鼠鲨科！
That's not what I'm asking!
我问的不是那个！
Why is it walking on human legs?
它为什么在用人腿走路？
The divers it ate probably turned into zombies
应该是被它吃掉的潜水员变成了僵尸
and are moving it.
在扛着它移动
Hold on, now! How does that make any sense?
等一下 那也太扯了吧？
How am I supposed to know?
我怎么知道？
What's that?
怎么了？
Why aren't we running?
为什么不跑了？
Zombies? There are some inside, as well?
僵尸？水族馆里面也有僵尸？
We can't go this way!
这条路行不通了！
I'm pretty sure there was a different emergency exit…
这里肯定还有其他紧急出口…
You're joking, right?
开什么玩笑呀？
This way! Hurry!
这边！快！
-Everyone, this way! -Hurry!
-大家往这边跑！ -快！
I don't want to die!
我不想死啊！
Hey! Calm down!
喂！你冷静点
I can't take it anymore!
我受够了！
Hurry!
快跑！
We're safe, somehow.
可算安全了
Huh?
那个…
Where's Miss Risk Analyst?
强调规避风险的小姐姐呢？
It's not my fault, it's not my fault…
不是我的错…
It's not my…
不是我的…
No way, is she still out there?
不会吧 她还在里面？
Are you serious? Damn it!
开什么玩笑？可恶！
It's no good! It's warped and won't open!
不好 门被挤变形了 打不开！
Akira! Help me out--
阿辉！来帮忙…
Hey…
喂
Akira?
阿辉？
Honestly…
真是的
This is why I hate working in big groups.
所以我才讨厌跟人群一起行动
Panic spreads like wildfire. I should've thought this through more.
恐慌会像野火一般蔓延 我真该更慎重考虑这点的
Incoming!
看招！
Why you… Stop struggling!
快给我…别挣扎了！
Akira?
阿辉？
Why?
为什么？
What are you doing here?
你怎么跑回来了？
Isn't it obvious?
这还不明显吗？
I'm here to save you.
我是来救你的呀
There's really something wrong with you! Why would you go so far as to do that?
你这人真是有毛病！ 为什么这么拼命呀？
Enough with all the reasons!
别凡事都讲求原因了！
When you're hungry, you want to eat your fill.
肚子饿了 会想吃饱
If you see a cute girl, you try to get to know her.
看见美女 会想认识
If I see someone who needs help, I want to be a hero!
看到有人需要帮助 我就会想当英雄！
Do I need a reason for everything?!
难道我做任何事都非要有理由吗？
Even so…
话虽如此
If you die, it's all over.
你要是死了 就什么都没有了
Why do you go so far to go straight for the things you want to do?
为什么你会为了想做的事情 如此不顾一切？
What's your strategy?
你有什么对策？
I don't have one in particular!
我没有特定的对策！
I thought so.
我想也是
-It's coming! -Okay!
-它来了！ -知道了！
This is bad!
情况不妙
I came here without thinking, but we aren't getting any chances.
我想都没想就冲回来救人 但这样下去毫无胜算！
-What should we do? What should-- -Akira!
-该怎么办？该怎么… -阿辉！
I have a plan!
我想到一个办法！
This is such a ridiculous idea that I can't believe it myself.
这个想法太荒诞了 连我自己都难以置信
Do you want to risk it?
你愿意冒险一试吗？
Sure!
当然！
Hold on. What are they doing?
慢着 他们在干什么？
I need to save them.
我得救救他们
I need to do something.
必须做点什么
Damn it.
可恶
I…
我…
I knew it. It's not here. Akira…
果然不在这儿 阿辉…
Okay! You want me to buy some time, right?
在！你要我帮你争取时间 对吗？
Come at me!
冲我来呀！
That was close.
好险
The Ampullae of Lorenzini?
劳伦氏腹壶？
That's right! Sharks have sensory organs in their heads
没错！鲨鱼的头部密布感觉器官
capable of detecting electric charges as small as one millionth of a volt.
能够感应到 哪怕只有百万分之一伏的微弱电荷
They use them to capture smaller fish based on the electrical field
它们正是利用这些器官 去感应小型鱼类肌肉产生的电场
that their muscles generate.
从而进行捕猎
A jolt of current to that sensitive organ from direct contact with a human's muscles
直接接触人体肌肉会对它敏感的器官 造成猛烈的电流震动
should confuse them enough to take it out!
导致混淆后就能轻易打倒它！
So, if we focus an attack there…
所以 只要瞄准攻击那里…
Yes! But it's still a bit unreliable.
是的！但这样还不够牢靠
I'd prefer to have something that can deliver a stronger electric current.
我们需要能造成更强电流冲击的东西
All right!
好的！
I still need to buy more time.
我还需要再争取一点时间
Damn it.
可恶
My body can't…
我的身体动不了…
Hey!
喂！
Look over here, sharky bastard!
看这边 笨鲨鱼！
Does this ass look tasty or what?!
这个屁屁看起来鲜嫩可口吗？
Grab a bite if you can!
有本事来咬一口呀！
Kencho.
阿宪
No! On second thought, don't eat me!
不要！我改主意了 别吃我！
What is a hero?
英雄究竟是什么？
What is…
怎样才算
a hero?
英雄？
A hero is…
英雄是…
Akira!
阿辉！
My target is the Ampullae of Lorenzini!
目标 劳伦氏腹壶！
Discharging a battery for maximum effect!
给电池放电 制造最强电流效果！
Will it work on a zombified shark?
用在僵尸鲨鱼身上会奏效吗？
I have no idea, but…
我不知道
We just have to test it out!
但是试试不就知道了！
Crackle Thunder…
电雷…
Punch!
神拳！
How was that? Miss! Kencho!
我刚才那招可还行？小姐姐！阿宪！
You nailed it! You're a total superhero!
你成功了！不愧是超级英雄！
Not that it's my business or anything…
或许是我多管闲事
But you've got bad taste in names.
但你起的名字都太烂俗了
Why are you leaving without saying anything?
大家为什么不说一声就走了呀？
Today, you were a real hero.
你今天可是名副其实的英雄呢
36. BECOME A SUPERHERO
（36 当超级英雄）
It's fine. Heroes don't need rewards.
安啦 英雄都是不求回报的
What about you?
你呢？
You okay not going with them?
真的不跟他们一起走吗？
We were only sharing a bus to the harbor.
我只是恰好跟他们 一起坐大巴来港口而已
Besides, I'm done with big groups.
况且 我受够了跟人群一起行动
What? You made a great team with Akira.
什么？你跟阿辉就合作得很好呀
What will you do? Will you take this opportunity…
你之后有什么打算？ 要不要趁此机会…
Out of the question.
不要
I figured not!
我想也是！
You idiot! Why are you pulling back?
你个白痴！干吗退缩啊？
Listen, the real attempts come after you're rejected.
听着 真正的尝试 都是在被拒绝之后才开始的
It's just like doing sales!
这跟做销售是一个道理
I was never in sales…
我从来没干过销售…
That's not what I meant.
那不是我要说的重点
What's the matter?
怎么了？
Did you forget something?
你忘东西了吗？
100 THINGS I WANT TO DO BEFORE BECOMING A ZOMBIE
（变成僵尸前想做的100件事）
My top priority is to do things to avoid becoming a zombie.
我的首要目标是避免变成僵尸
But you two just want to do things before becoming a zombie.
而你们两个只想在变成僵尸之前 尽可能地完成心愿
Our methods are incompatible.
我们的生存法则互不相容
One more thing.
还有一件事
Despite all my warnings,
你不顾我的劝阻
you still risked those precious to you to save a stranger like myself.
仍然抛下重要的伙伴 来救像我这样不相干的人
I don't have enough lives to work together with--
我没那么多条命可以陪你玩…
Yeah, but…
对 可是
You're someone precious to me now, Miss.
你现在对我来说 也是很重要的人呀 小姐姐
I'd save you even if I wasn't trying to be a hero.
就算不是为了当英雄 我也会去救你的
Hey, Miss?
喂 小姐姐？
What's the matter?
怎么了？
Where will you be going now?
你现在要去哪里？
Let's see…
我想想看
Wherever I can find a place that's safe and sustainable.
我要找一个安全 并且能够长久停留的地方
Who knows if a safe place really exists.
谁知道呢？ 也许根本就不存在安全的地方了
I almost forgot.
差点忘了
Here, this is my QR code.
给 这是我的二维码
I'm sure we'll never meet again.
想必我们以后不会再见了
There isn't much risk in sharing contact information with you.
所以跟你分享联系方式 也没多大风险啦
SHIZUKA MIKAZUKI ADD FRIEND
（三日月闲加好友）
Shizuka Mikazuki.
三日月闲
I hope I can see her again!
真希望还能再见到她！
So, what will we do now?
那我们现在要干什么？
Let's see…
让我想想看
Before I've realized it, it's been seven years since I moved here.
不知不觉间 我搬来东京已经有七个年头了
I met Kencho in college
我在大学认识了阿宪
and tasted intense despair working at an exploitative company.
在黑心企业品尝了绝望的滋味
I came here, awed by the glitz and glamor of the big city, but…
我当初受到 大城市的繁华与魅力所吸引搬来这里
Yeah! I think I've had my fill of Tokyo.
没错！东京我已经待够了
I want my parents to see that I'm doing okay.
我想让爸妈看看 我现在过得很好
Well then, let's go!
那好 我们出发吧！
Yeah! To Kanto's best-kept secret! Gunma!
好嘞！向关东的神秘瑰宝进发！ 群马 我们来啦！
Next time: RV of the Dead.
下一集：《死者的露营车》